# **Ugo Landini**

Manager & Software Craftsman

via Centuripe 11
00179 Rome, Italy
T+39 346 3350669
ugo.landini@gmail.com
https://ugol.io

# **Objective**

To drive business growth by leveraging cutting-edge technology, consultative sales, and strategic customer engagement in dynamic and challenging environments.

# **Summary**

With over 25 years of experience in software development and IT, I specialize in helping businesses unlock value through Data Streaming, Data Management, and Application Integration. As a Senior Manager at Confluent, I guide enterprises in adopting real-time streaming solutions that enhance efficiency, innovation, and revenue growth. My expertise extends beyond technology to business strategy, customer success, and solution consulting, enabling me to bridge the gap between technical solutions and business outcomes.

# **Professional Experience**

Throughout my career, I have played key roles in pre-sales, post-sales, and consultative engagements, helping customers implement high-impact solutions. I have a strong track record of influencing stakeholders, identifying business needs, and translating them into technology strategies that drive revenue and competitive advantage. My experience spans solution architecture, enterprise adoption strategy, and executive-level advisory, ensuring that technical solutions align with business goals.

# **Teaching and Communication**

As an experienced speaker and educator, I have a proven ability to convey complex technical concepts to diverse audiences, from students to developers to C-level executives. I have led high-impact presentations, conducted strategic workshops, and contributed to sales enablement initiatives. My ability to articulate value propositions has made me a key contributor in pre-sales engagements, customer advocacy, and thought leadership initiatives.

# **Community Engagement**

I have played an active role in shaping the IT industry through leadership in developer communities and large-scale events. As the former president of JUG Roma and CTO of Codemotion, I have built influential networks of different people at different levels. My presence at international conferences, including Red Hat Summit, Javapolis and Data in Motion has reinforced my reputation as a trusted advisor in the field.

# Open Source Contributions

A passionate advocate for Open Source, I have contributed to key projects that have influenced the industry, including JR, HACEP, Apache Camel, and JGroups RAFT. My entrepreneurial mindset has also led to successful software products, such as my Pomodoro app for Mac, which gained recognitions from Apple.

via Centuripe 11 00179 Rome, Italy **T** +39 346 3350669 ugo.landini@gmail.com https://ugol.io

# **Experience:**

#### Senior Manager @ Confluent

2023-now

 SE Manager for Italy/Iberia. Working within the customer success team to help our clients attain maximum value from data streaming.

#### JR founder/lead architect

2023-now

- JR is the lead open source synthetic data generation tool
- https://jrnd.io/
- https://github.com/jrnd-io/jr

# Staff Solutions Engineer @ Confluent

2019-2022

· Everything about Kafka and the Distributed Data streaming world.

# **HACEP** founder/lead architect

2016-2018

- HACEP is an highly available and scalable version of Drools CEP. It's the official Red Hat reference architecture for an Enterprise CEP
- https://access.redhat.com/articles/2542881
- http://redhat-italy.github.io/hacep/

#### **Principal Solution Architect @ Red Hat**

2012-2019

- Solution Architect, specialised in everything related to middleware.
- · Camel committer (camel-couchbase), JGroups RAFT committer

#### **Lead Architect @ VMWare**

2012

· VFabric Architect, specialised in RabbitMQ and Gemfire projects

#### Founder @ YMobe

2012 - 2014

Utility and Game Developing for iOS (Pomodoro app and other casual games)

#### CTO Office @ Poste Italiane

2008

- 2012
- Head of ESB/Internet applications
- Some public slides: <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ugolandini/25-tiers">http://www.slideshare.net/ugolandini/25-tiers</a>

#### Founder @ Codemotion

2006 - 2015

• Founder and CTO of Codemotion (ex Javaday) http://www.codemotion.it/en

#### **CTO @ Sourcesense/Pronetics**

2006 - 2008

 Responsible for the overall technical strategies and handling directly a team of 25 presales/postsales people

#### Founder @ JUG Roma

2005 - 2012

· President and founder of JUG Roma

# Senior Architect @ Sun Microsystems

2003 - 2006

 Architected and designed an ESB for Italian eGovernment, which became a local Italian Sun product.

I authorize the collection and processing of my personal data (according to the italian 675/96 law and similar ones)

via Centuripe 11
00179 Rome, Italy
T+39 346 3350669
ugo.landini@gmail.com
https://ugol.io

 Worked as a consultant/mentor/coach on EAI projects for top Sun customers (INPS, Acea, NCR, Telecom, Regione Toscana among the others)

# Team leader @ Sun Microsystems

2000 - 2003

- Managed Enterprise Java Instructors (30 people) in Italy for Sun Educational Services
- Mentored Sun Professional Services Java Architects on Design and Methodological issues

# CTO @ EuropeanArtisans.com (RM/NY)

1999 - 2000

- · Designed the architecture for EuropeanArtisans.com, an US startup
- Led a 10 people team in Rome, experimenting eXtreme Programming practices

# Team leader @ CGIL Lombardia/CCOO Catalunya (MI)

1998 - 1999

- Designed the Spiderwork framework to help the development of a full Object Oriented n-tier Java/Corba application
- Led a 4 people team, won a prize at Softech 2000 for Software Development Best Practice

#### Team leader @ OIS Italia

1997 - 1998

- Led a 6 people team for Analysis and Design of a Distributed Software
- · Approached the emerging world of Middleware and EAI (Fortè)

# Teacher @ PRAEL Sistemi

1996 - 1997

• Taught a wide range of courseware, from Office Automation to OOAD ones

# Owner @ Shark snc

1994 - 1996

Founded Shark snc, a software factory targeting small business

# Entrepreneur @ Honeywell bull

1989 - 1990

 Created my first commercial software to manage Automobil Club Italia (ACI) subagencies, later sold to Honeywell Bull

# **Public Speeches and Prizes**

| Big Data Week           | Synthetic data generation                  | 2024   |
|-------------------------|--|--------|
| Codemotion              | Lesson learned from developing JR          | 2024   |
| Data in Motion          | Keynote and tech track lead                | 2023/4 |
| Geek talk               | Interview                                  | 2022   |
| Confluent               | KSQL and Stream webinar                    | 2021   |
| Confluent               | Kafka webinar                              | 2020   |
| Red Hat Summit          | JDG & Instant Payment                      | 2018   |
| Red Hat Summit          | HACEP lab                                  | 2017   |
| Open Source Day         | MSA & Openshift                            | 2016   |
| Open Source Day         | Fuse Fabric Techlab                        | 2014   |
| Open Source Day         | JDG Techlab                                | 2013   |
| Codemotion              | Modern Cloud Integration with Fabric       | 2013   |
| Better Software, WhyMCA | Mobile Programming in LUA                  | 2011   |
| Javaday IV              | 2.5 tiers architecture                     | 2010   |
| Javapolis, Javaday II   | Clustering a real word app with Terracotta | 2007   |
| Javaday II              | Treasure troves of open source             | 2007   |
| Javaday I               | Java Memory Model & Concurrency            | 2006   |
|                         |  |        |

via Centuripe 11 00179 Rome, Italy **T** +39 346 3350669 ugo.landini@gmail.com https://ugol.io

Sun Java Conference **Object Oriented Principles** 

2002/3/4

Consorzio Nettuno TV Java course (RAI), still aired 2001 **UML Day** UML and method(ologie)s 2001 Softech 2000 Software Development Best Practice 2000

# **Papers**

| JR tutorial part I                        | 2023  |
|---|---|
| Infoq JGroups RAFT                        | 2015  |
| "Idiomatica" series                       | 2006  |
| Fragile Base Class                        | 2004  |
| articles & book reviews                   | 2003  |
| Thesis tutor on "Distributed Programming" | 1999  |
| Computer Programming magazine n.97        | 1999  |
|   | Infoq JGroups RAFT "Idiomatica" series Fragile Base Class articles & book reviews Thesis tutor on "Distributed Programming" |

# **Open Source & Public software**

JR Synthetic data generation <a href="https://jrnd.io/">https://jrnd.io/</a>

**HACEP** Highly Available CEP http://redhat-italy.github.io/hacep/

Github Personal page https://github.com/ugol

# **Education and training**

Università La Sapienza Math (uncompleted)

Computer Science G.Vallauri

Management Crucial conversations (Red Hat), Associate Man-

ager Program (Red Hat), Manager Program and Advanced Manager Program (Confluent)

Sales MEDDPICC sales course (Red Hat)

#### **Professional certifications and Memberships**

- Mensa High IQ Society (top 1%)
- JUG Roma president
- Sun certified Enterprise Architect, Sun certified Java Programmer, JBoss certified specialist, Kafka developer and administration, many others

For more detailed information about my work and contributions, please visit my LinkedIn profile: http://it.linkedin.com/in/ugolandini.